<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the Honourable House of Commons at St. Margaret's Westminster, upon the 16th of April, 1696 being a day of thanksgiving unto Almighty God for discovering and disappointing an horrid and barbarous conspiracy of papists and other traiterous persons to assassinate and murder His Most Gracious Majesty's royal person and for delivering this kingdom from an invasion intended by the French / by Samuel Barton ...</title>
            <author>Barton, Samuel, 1647 or 8-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31112</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B993</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4253</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13078801</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13078801</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97219</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31112)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97219)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 407:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the Honourable House of Commons at St. Margaret's Westminster, upon the 16th of April, 1696 being a day of thanksgiving unto Almighty God for discovering and disappointing an horrid and barbarous conspiracy of papists and other traiterous persons to assassinate and murder His Most Gracious Majesty's royal person and for delivering this kingdom from an invasion intended by the French / by Samuel Barton ...</title>
                  <author>Barton, Samuel, 1647 or 8-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Cockerill, Senr. and Junr. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:97219:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97219:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97219:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97219:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>BARTON</hi>'s THANSGIVING-SERMON Before the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS, <hi>APRIL</hi> 16. 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:97219:3"/>
            <head>Veneris <hi>17.</hi> die Aprilis <hi>1696.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>Ordered,</opener>
            <p>THAT the Thanks of this Houſe be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Mr. <hi>Barton</hi> for the Sermon preach'd before them yeſterday at St. <hi>Margaret's Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> and that he be deſired to print the ſame; and that Mr. <hi>Conyers</hi> do acquaint him therewith.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Paul Jodrell,</hi> Cl. Dom. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97219:3"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the Honourable <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> AT St. MARGARET'S WESTMINSTER, Upon the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> 1696.</p>
            <p>BEING A Day of THANKSGIVING unto Almighty God, for Diſcovering and Diſappointing an Horrid and Barbarous Conſpiracy of Papiſts and other Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Perſons to Aſſaſſinate and Murder his Moſt Gracious Majeſty's Royal Perſon; and for Delivering this Kingdom from an Invaſion intended by the <hi>French</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL BARTON,</hi> B. D. Chaplain to the Houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Cockerill,</hi> Sen<hi rend="sup">r</hi> and Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, at the <hi>Three Legs</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> MDCXCVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:97219:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97219:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd before the Honourable Houſe of Commons, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALM LXXV. 1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thee, O God, do we give thanks; unto thee do we give thanks; For that thy name is near, thy wondrous works declare.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F we reflect on the Wicked and Traiterous Deſigns of our Enemies, and think how near they lately were to put 'em in execution, and what the Conſequences of that muſt have been; we cannot but ſee cauſe to acknowledge God's Goodneſs, to adore his Wonderful and Gracious Providence,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97219:5"/>and to think our ſelves exceeding happy, in that we are now here peaceably met together, to render our devour Praiſes and Thankſgivings unto him, and not driven from home, or ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd up and down under the Fears and Terrors of Foreign Armies ravaging amongſt us, or of a more Unnatural Brood of Vipers amongſt our ſelves, that were to have join'd with 'em for the Ruin of their own Religion (as they call it), and of their Countrey. From theſe woful Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities that were haſtily coming upon us, and muſt, in all human appearance, before this time have overtaken us, Not our own Policy and Foreſight, not any Wiſdom or good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct that we can boaſt of, but the mere over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling Hand of Divine Providence, the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of that God who ſees through all the dark Plots and Conſpiracies of his own and his Church's Enemies, have mercifully deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd us.</p>
            <p>This, as well as many former Deliverances that we have had, is of ſuch a nature, that it plainly ſpeaks him to be the Author of it. And it ſhould therefore engage us to the moſt chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and hearty Thankſgivings, to reiterated Acts of Praiſe and grateful Acknowledgment, and ſhould teach us to aſcribe the Glory of all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97219:5"/>to him, who in ſo viſible and remarkable a manner has appeared from time to time, moſt opportunely to help and deliver us. I ſuppoſe therefore the Words which I have choſen as the Subject of my Diſcourſe at this time, will be allow'd to be proper and pertinent enough to the Occaſion.</p>
            <p>They are part of a Pſalm which, as ſome conjecture, was compos'd by <hi>Aſaph</hi> the Seer (mention'd 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.30.) as a Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for the great Deliverance that God wrought for <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and the People of the <hi>Jews,</hi> from <hi>Senacherib</hi> the King of <hi>Aſſyria.</hi> And if this were ſo, then we may underſtand the <hi>Al-taſchith</hi> that is in the Title, to be not merely, as ſome would have it, a Note to direct how the Pſalm was to be ſung, but to be put as an Alluſion to what the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> had foretold concerning <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacherib, viz.</hi> That for all his proud Boaſting and his Confidence, <hi>he ſhould not come into Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 37, 33.</note> 
               <hi>nor ſhoot an arrow there:</hi> For ſo the Word <hi>Al-taſchith</hi> ſignifies; <hi>Let him not deſtroy;</hi> or, <hi>He ſhall not deſtroy.</hi> Which Senſe of it need not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, though we ſhould ſuppoſe this Pſalm to have been made (as others think it was) long before the days of <hi>Hezekiah, viz.</hi> as an Hymn of Thankſgiving for <hi>David</hi>'s happy Settlement
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97219:6"/>upon the Throne, after the many Troubles and Difficulties which he met with in his way to it. For then it may refer to <hi>Saul,</hi> and the Fruſtration of all his Attempts to take away <hi>David</hi>'s Life. But however it were, we may obſerve in the Words theſe Two Things; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. A Devout, Emphatical, and Repeated Thankſgiving; <hi>Unto thee, O God, do we give Thanks; unto thee do we give Thanks;</hi> where the Reduplication of the Expreſſion intimates to us, That the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> thought there was abundant Cauſe to give Thanks to God; yea, that the Thanks were peculiarly due to him, in a manner far tranſcending all that could be due to Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or ſubordinate Cauſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Reaſon added, why they ought to be more than ordinarily thankful unto God; <hi>viz.</hi> Becauſe the Deliverance was ſuch as plainly pointed out him for its Author. <hi>For that thy Name is near,</hi> i. e. that thou art near by thy Power and Goodneſs to help and ſave us, <hi>thy wondrous works declare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the Occaſion of this Pſalm were the Deliverance from <hi>Senacherib,</hi> 'tis plain then that there was great Cauſe of Thankſgiving. For then both King and People had been in extreme danger. And had <hi>Senacherib</hi> prevail'd, the City
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97219:6"/>of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had in all probability been ſpoil'd and laid waſte, the Holy Temple of God viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and prophan'd, great numbers of people ſlain with the Sword, and the reſt carried into a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Captivity. Neither had they any ſufficient Strength of their own to defend or preſerve themſelves from theſe threatning Evils, but the work was done for 'em by an Angel, who went out with God's Commiſſion and ſlew in one Night a Hundred and fourſcore and five thouſand of the Enemy. So that this was a thing wholly extraordinary.</p>
            <p>But if the Occaſion of this <hi>Pſalm</hi> were <hi>David</hi>'s happy Settlement upon the Throne, after many years patient waiting, many dangers and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips undergone; Then have we indeed not any direct or downright Miracle demonſtrating the Name of God to be near, or his Power and Goodneſs to be exercis'd and diſplay'd in the Tranſaction, but a viſible Series of many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Events, whereby God brought to paſs what he intended and had foretold; and which an obſerving Beholder, that was concern'd in 'em, might well call. <hi>Wondrous Works,</hi> though there were no Violence offer'd to the Courſe of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor nothing done wherein Second Cauſes had not their ſubordinate Agency as uſual, under
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97219:7"/>him who is the Grand Diſpoſer of all things for his own Glory, and his People's Good.</p>
            <p>Since therefore by <hi>Wondrous Works</hi> 'tis not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for us to underſtand ſuch as are in the ſtricteſt ſenſe Miraculous, but rather Signal and Remarkable Providences, I ſuppoſe we may fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make from the Text theſe Two following Obſervations; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That as all things are order'd by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, ſo there are ſome Events that deſerve the name of Special Providences, for that they ſhew forth the Power, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs of God, and his Care over his Church and People in a more eſpecial and extraordinary manner than others do.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That 'tis our Duty to obſerve and take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of ſuch Events, to render God the Glory, and to offer unto him our hearty Praiſes and Thankſgivings for the Benefit or Deliverance that we receive thereby.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſpeak ſomething to each of theſe, and then proceed to make ſome Application to the preſent Occaſion. And</p>
            <p n="1">1. That as all things are order'd by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, ſo there are ſome Events that deſerve the name of Special Providences, for that they ſhew forth the Power, Wiſdom, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97219:7"/>Goodneſs of God, and his Care over his Church and People in a more eſpecial and extraordinary manner than others do.</p>
            <p>That all Human Affairs are order'd by God's Providence, ſo that without his Knowledge and Permiſſion at the leaſt, nothing can poſſibly come to paſs, yea, that he is able to bring about whatever he pleaſes, This is a Truth ſo bright and clear, that it was ſcarce ever, I think, denied by any that own'd a God who was the Creator of the World: For it were too abſurd to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that God ſhould make the World, and not be the Governor of it. And though indeed we are no more able to give a Reaſon of all the Proceedings of the Divine Providence, than we are to explain all the Works of Nature; yet as in the latter we ſee enough to convince us of his Infinite Power, Wiſdom, and Bounty to his Creatures, ſo in the former alſo we may eaſily ſee ſufficient Proofs of the ſame his moſt Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Perfections. But all the Works of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence are not alike. Sometimes for wiſe and good Reaſons God has been pleas'd quite to alter the Courſe of Nature, as it were to ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to have a Power above it. So it was when he divided the Sea, and made the Waters to ſtand on an heap, whilſt the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> paſſed through:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97219:8"/>So likewiſe in many other his Miraculous Works that we read of in Holy Scripture, both of the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>In the general Courſe of Things, Second Cauſes ſeem as if they were left to themſelves, and tempt inconſiderate men ſometimes to think that they are ſo: But there are very frequently ſuch Events brought to paſs, that are, as it were, of a Middle Sort, not plainly Miraculous, nor yet Common and Ordinary, but carrying in 'em very peculiar Marks and Characters of the Divine Power, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs, and of his Care of Good Men, or of his Truth and Faithfulneſs to his Promiſes or Predictions. And theſe we call Special and Signal Providences.</p>
            <p>Such was that whereby <hi>Joſeph</hi> was brought into <hi>Egypt;</hi> and the Ill will and Envy of his Brethren, as well as his Miſtreſs her falſe Accuſations after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, turn'd to the great advantage and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs both of himſelf and his Family; and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Predictions thereby alſo fulfill'd. Such was that whereby <hi>David</hi> was advanced to the Throne from the mean Calling of a Shepherd. By ſuch a ſignal Providence it was that he married one of the Daughters of <hi>Saul,</hi> though much againſt the good liking of her Father,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 18.21.</note> only that he hoped (the Text tells us) <hi>that ſhe would become a ſnare to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97219:8"/>him,</hi> in which he proved to be much miſtaken. And by the like Providence was he preſerved from time to time, from all the Attempts of his Father-in-law to aſſaſſinate him, and, at laſt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Tragical Death, both of <hi>Saul</hi> and his Son <hi>Iſhboſheth,</hi> ſetled peaceably in the Kingdom which God had promiſed him.</p>
            <p>By ſuch a ſignal and remarkable Providence was the whole Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> delivered from the Deſtruction and Extirpation deſigned againſt 'em by <hi>Haman,</hi> and he himſelf hang'd on the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Gallows he had prepared for <hi>Mordecai.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might add many more Inſtances out of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and innumerable there are to be found in other Hiſtories. But to come a little nearer our own Times, and to ſuch things as are of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar concernment to our ſelves. The Conduct of Divine Providence was very obſervable in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about a Reformation of Religion in the Church, and particularly in theſe Nations.</p>
            <p>That in <hi>Germany</hi> ſuch a man as <hi>Luther</hi> ſhould be rais'd up, with a Spirit fit to encounter the Difficulties of that work for which he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned; That the groſs and notorious corruption of Indulgences, preach'd about at that time in a ſhameleſs manner, to delude and cheat the People, ſhould give him the occaſion of enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97219:9"/>and that the Oppoſition he met with, ſhould only ſerve to whet him, and put him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on examining farther, and diſcovering ſtill more Errors and Abuſes, which in thoſe dark Ages had been put upon the Chriſtian World; that no means ſhould be found to take him off, or to hinder the ſpreading of his Doctrine, though it were ſo vehemently endeavoured by the Great Ones of thoſe days; and that whole Countreys ſhould thereupon revolt, and caſting off their Obedience to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> together with the Errors they had ſuck'd in thence, ſhould return to the Primitive and Apoſtolical Chriſtianity: The carrying on, and management of all theſe things by the Divine Providence, affords a very wonderful Scene to him that ſeriouſly and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately takes a view of it, and obſerves how hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily things then concurred to bring that about, in God's appointed time, which to man might have juſtly ſeem'd impoſſible; and how vain were all the ſtrivings, and earneſt Endeavours of the Great Ones of the World to hinder what God had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to bring to paſs; even juſt like the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of the Heathen Emperors to ſuppreſs Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>In our own Nation how remarkable was the Providence of God that made uſe of an High-ſpirited
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97219:9"/>Prince, a zealous Aſſertor of the Popiſh Cauſe, and a Writer againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> to lay the Foundations of a Reformation amongſt us, and to remove thoſe Obſtacles, thoſe Nurſeries, I mean, of Idolatry and Superſtition, which would elſe have render'd the Work impoſſible (in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) to his Succeſſors! So that it might be ſaid according to <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Riddle,<note place="margin">Judges 14.14.</note> That <hi>out of the eater came forth meat!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis very obſervable alſo, how much the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion here was eſtabliſh'd, and made to take the deeper root in the hearts of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, inſtead of being rooted out by the Blood of the Martyrs, which was ſhed in ſuch abundance, during the ſhort Reign of Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> And how it was legally ſetled under the long and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py one of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> As alſo, how ſhe, whilſt ſhe ſtrictly adher'd to it, was all along wonderfully preſerv'd from the Deſigns and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations of her Enemies, which were many and dangerous; and yet ſerv'd to no other purpoſe but to knit the hearts of her Subjects the more cloſely to her, and to unite them in mutual Bands of Aſſociation to do all that in them lay to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve her Life.</p>
            <p>I might ſpeak alſo of the ſtrange, but happy Diſcovery of the <hi>Gun-powder Plot</hi> in the following Reign. But I ſhould be too long ſhould I deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to more Particulars.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:97219:10"/>
            <p> I proceed therefore to ſpeak to the Second Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition that was drawn from the words, which was,</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is our duty to obſerve and take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the ſignal Providences of God; to render unto him the Glory of them; and to offer him our hearty Praiſes and Thankſgivings for the Benefit or Deliverance that we receive by them.</p>
            <p>There are two Extreams that men are apt to run into in this matter. The one is, of thoſe who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrue Providence always in favour of themſelves, or their own Party; and if Good befal us, preſently reckon it is for their ſakes; or if Evil come, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately conclude, 'Tis becauſe we will not do as they would have us, tho perhaps there is very little Reaſon that we ſhould. The other Extream is, of ſuch as are ſo careleſs and inconſiderate, as to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look the hand of God whatever falls out, though never ſo remarkable, never ſo ſeaſonable, never ſo ſurprizing and unexpected, or never ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, in all appearance, for the ſupport and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of True Religion, or for the bringing of ſome juſt Judgment upon great and notorious Offenders. Such there are, who ſeem to impute all to ſecond Cauſes, ſcarce ever looking higher; or elſe, at leaſt, to imagine, that all things are ſo promiſcuouſly order'd by Providence, that it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies nothing to take any notice what falls out.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97219:10"/>
            <p> But the true and middle way which we ought to take between theſe Extreams, is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt.</hi> Never to look on the meer ſeeming fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Providence alone, as a ſufficient Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the goodneſs of any Cauſe, for that will be found a very dangerous and uncertain way of Arguing. But yet,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> When we are from other Reaſons well ſatisfied of the Goodneſs or Juſtice of a Cauſe, or the Truth of any Profeſſion, to take a particular notice then of what Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence does in favour of it, and to believe that, tho' indeed it be true, that in the general courſe of God's Providence things are ſomewhat pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly carried (as 'tis reaſonable they ſhould, ſince God deſigns this Life for a time of Trial) yet, as he is ever a lover of good Men, and a Friend to thoſe that fear him, ſo he will ſo far appear in their defence, as never to ſuffer Piety, true Religion and Vertue to be utterly run down and deſtroy'd, as they wou'd certainly be, did not his Providence ſometimes interpoſe, and appear for 'em. And for that Reaſon, God does ſometimes ſignally ſhew himſelf for their Defence, and Preſervation, and for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding of their Enemies. And when he does
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97219:11"/>do ſo, for us to take no notice of it, is an Argument of great ſtupidity, Ingratitude, and Folly. They are highly blam'd in Scripture, who <hi>regard not the work of the Lord, nor conſider the operation of his hands;</hi> they are <hi>the bruitiſh among the People,</hi> who look no farther than the immediate Agents or Inſtruments whereby ſuch things are done, and caſt no Eye upwards to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, who ſits in the Heaven above, and beholds all the dwellers upon Earth, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders every thing that falls out among 'em, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rules of a moſt Exquiſite and Unſearchable Wiſdom. The paſſing over ſuch things without any regard, is a robbing God of the Glory of his Works, and of the Praiſe that is due unto him, as well as a depriving our ſelves of the Benefit and Comfort that we might and ought to take in the Performance of ſo Excellent and Noble a Duty, as that of rendring Praiſe, and Honour, and Thankſgiving to our Great Creator.</p>
            <p>It becomes every Good and Religious Man, in all ſuch Caſes, when he ſees the Innocent happily preſer'd from intended Ruine, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of true Religion reſcued from imminent Danger, Miſchievous and Traiterous Plotters
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97219:11"/>and Conſpirators ſurprizingly diſcover'd, and brought to Condign Puniſhment, Tyrants and Perſecutors diſappointed in their Barbarous and Bloody Deſigns, and God's Judgments perhaps remarkably executed upon 'em. 'Tis the part, I ſay, of every Good and Religious Man, in ſuch a Caſe, to Admire and Adore God's Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Wiſdom and Power, to applaud his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and his Goodneſs to his People, and to Rejoyce and Triumph in the Event. So the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> tells us in ſuch Caſes, <hi>The Righteous ſhall ſee it, and rejoyce, and all Iniquity ſhall ſtop her mouth, Pſal.</hi> 107.42. And in divers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he Exhorts to this Duty, particularly <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Let all thoſe that put their truſt in God rejoyce, let them ever ſhout for joy, becauſe thou defendeſt them.</hi> And in the Book of the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi> the Saints and all the whole Heav'ns are call'd upon to rejoyce at the fall of <hi>Babylon. Rejoyce over her thou Heaven, and ye Holy Apoſtles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.20.</note> 
               <hi>and Prophets, for God hath avenged you on her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I now proceed in the laſt place, to make ſome Application of this Diſcourſe to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Occaſion. And here I ſhall,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider how very Remarkable and Signal our preſent Deliverance is, which ſhou'd
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97219:12"/>induce us to the more heedful obſervance, and devout admiration of the Providence of God in it. And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall conſider how beneficial and happy a Deliverance it is to us, in order to the increaſing of our Thankfulneſs, and putting us upon a ſuitable Carriage towards God.</p>
            <p>Now our preſent Deliverance will appear to be very Remarkable, whether we conſider either,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Circumſtances of it; Or,</item>
               <item>2. For whom it is wrought; Or,</item>
               <item>3. What Ends and Deſigns of Providence are anſwer'd by it. And,</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. For the Circumſtances of it. If we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it, as indeed it is, but a part, and a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther carrying on of that great Work which God has been doing theſe ſeveral years paſt in this part of the World, and particularly amongſt us of theſe Nations, we cannot but think it very ſuitable, and of a piece with all the reſt; nor can we chuſe but reflect on the whole, as on a wonderful Scene of Providence, fit to be taken notice of, and admir'd. In order whereunto, it will be neceſſary for us to call to mind that, which one wou'd think none ſhou'd eaſily for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, <hi>viz.</hi> What our Condition was, and what
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97219:12"/>the ſtate of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> abroad, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the late happy Revolution. As for our ſelves, you cannot but remember by what haſty ſteps we were going towards Popery, and how fearful and apprehenſive we then generally were of it, as having no viſible means to prevent its being forcibly obtruded upon us, together with a new Conſtitution of Government, according to the Pattern of a Neighbouring Nation. In <hi>France</hi> you all know how the Profeſſors of the Reform'd Religion were perſecuted in a new and unheard of manner, which has prevail'd to an utter Extirpation of the open profeſſion of it. And ſo great was the Power and Influence of <hi>France,</hi> that it did not appear how either we, or any of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> abroad, in the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that things were, cou'd poſſibly reſiſt or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the execution of thoſe two grand Deſigns, that were viſibly enough on foot, of Extirpating the <hi>Northern Hereſie</hi> (as they call'd it) and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up an <hi>Univerſal Monarchy.</hi> This I take to be but a true repreſentation of our Caſe as it then was, when all on a ſudden God was pleas'd to bring about one of the moſt wonderful and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing Revolutions that any Age has ever ſeen. His preſent Majeſty, with a ſmall number of Forces came over to <hi>Deliver</hi> us from that yoak
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97219:13"/>of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery</hi> that was juſt a going to be put on. It was a great wonder that he would venture upon ſo bold and hazardous an Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, and no leſs that he ſhould find an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to do it. Whether the Enemy diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd not the Deſign time enough to hinder it, or whether he imagin'd ſuch an Expedition would end but in the ruine of the Undertaker. Take it either way, the Providence was very Remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; and when His Majeſty, the then Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> was ready to come, you all remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how ſeaſonably and happily God was pleas'd to order the Winds to come about to favour his Arrival, and at the ſame time to prevent the late King's Fleet from making any oppoſition. That Circumſtance of the Wind I am ſure was very Remarkable, and then much talk'd of; for God gave juſt enough to do the buſineſs, and then immediately, when it had as it were executed its Commiſſion, it chop'd about again. And truly the turning about the hearts of the People ſo Univerſally at that time, and making even thoſe that were pitch'd upon as the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to bring us into Slavery, ſo readily go over to the other ſide, was a Circumſtance not leſs, but rather much more Remarkable than that of the Wind; yea the more ſo ſtill,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97219:13"/>becauſe like that too, as ſoon as the Buſineſs was well over, divers of them quickly turn'd about again, as unaccountably as the Wind it ſelf, which our Saviour tells us <hi>blows where it liſteth,</hi> no Man being able to ſay why from this Corner, rather than from that. But here now there open'd a new Scene of Affairs; and I ſhou'd be too long, ſhou'd I reckon up all the Remarkable Providences that have attended the preſent War in which we are Engag'd. However this is viſible and clear, that the Succeſſes we have had, have been ſtill owing very much to ſome ſignal Interpoſitions of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; as particularly that at <hi>La Hogue,</hi> when the Wind was again ſo favourable as to keep off the Enemie's Fleet, 'till juſt we were ready for it; and then to deliver a good part of it into our hands. But to come to the Occaſion of our preſent meeting. The War growing tedious, it ſeems at laſt the Enemy had reſolv'd to make a Deſcent upon <hi>England;</hi> and truly he had <hi>pitch'd</hi> upon a time that ſeem'd very favourable to ſuch a Deſign; A time when he might hope the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the War ſo long, together with ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Circumſtances we have of late lain under, might make a Raſh and Heady People ready for another Change, altho' apparently to their Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, if they had but eyes open to ſee it. A
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97219:14"/>time when very few of our Regulated Troops were in the Kingdom. A time when by Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they had aſſurances from hence of a Party that would riſe and joyn 'em at their Landing. Tho' it be a thing wonderful (even to aſtoniſhment) that any among us ſhou'd be ſo mad; that any <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Man, eſpecially that calls himſelf a <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,</hi> ſhou'd have ſo little regard either to his Religion, or his Native Country, as upon any Account to Deſire and Incourage the bringing over a <hi>French</hi> Army hither; but ſuch it ſeems there were too many. A Time it was more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over when our Fleet was to have been gone far enough off, and had been actually gone above a Month before, if the Wind again wou'd have permitted 'em to obey their Orders. Yea, which was worſt of all, it was a Time when a Crew of Ruffians (by whoſe Commiſſion or Inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the World muſt judge) even juſt about ſuch a number as Conſpir'd againſt St. <hi>Paul,</hi> had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed together in a moſt Horrid and Barbarous Deſign to Aſſaſſinate our King. A Time certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this was, upon all accounts, very proper for the <hi>French</hi> to make an Invaſion! And no doubt they reckon'd themſelves in a manner ſure of the Succeſs.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97219:14"/>
            <p> But here again, behold the wonderful Hand of God! Yea 'tis fit for us to ſtand ſtill and pauſe a while to admire his Providence! For our Fleet ſhou'd indeed have ſail'd, but the Wind for a matter of two Months together hung ſtill in one Corner and wou'd not ſuffer it. Our Allies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad having ſome Apprehenſion of our Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, prepar'd to ſend us back our Soldiers to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend us; And, which was more than all the reſt, The Project for the Aſſaſſination (that damnable and helliſh Deſign) is happily diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd and diſappointed. And now inſtead of a <hi>French</hi> Invaſion, we have been lying with a large Fleet upon their Coaſts; Inſtead of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving our King barbarouſly murder'd, God has given him the Necks of his Enemies, yea we have the Heads of divers of thoſe Miſcreants upon our City Gates. Inſtead of an Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on among our ſelves, we have, God be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, a good Number of the Contrivers of it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm'd and ſecur'd. Inſtead of any Commotions from a Diſcontented People weary of the War; we find the People of <hi>England</hi> generally wiſer than to think to eaſe themſelves by ſuch abſurd Means; nay, on the contrary unanimouſly aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciating to do their utmoſt for the Defence and Preſervation of his Majeſty's Sacred Perſon and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97219:15"/>Government; Yea, looking upon him (as there is great Reaſon they ſhou'd) as a particular Gift from Heaven, ſent us in the moſt needful time for our Deliverance! A Prince in whom all the Virtues of his Anceſtors ſhine very bright, and who, like them too, but in a more high and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent degree, has that peculiar Honour done him by the wiſe Providence of God, to be ſet as the Bulwark of True Religion, the Patron of Laws and Liberties, and the Grand Oppoſer of Tyranny and Oppreſſion in all this part of the World. So that now (thanks be to Almighty God) inſtead of the Clergy of <hi>France</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their People upon that Text in the 46th of <hi>Jeremiah, verſ.</hi> 10. which, 'tis ſaid, was put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout amongſt 'em as a proper Subject upon this Occaſion of their intended Deſcent, and the Succeſs they expected in it; <hi>viz. This is the Day of the Lord of Hoſts, a Day of Vengeance, that he may avenge himſelf of his Adverſaries; And the Sword ſhall devour, and it ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate and made drunk with Blood; For the Lord of Hoſts hath a Sacrifice in the North Country.</hi> Inſtead of this, I ſay, we may with better Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon take up the following words at the next Verſe of that Chapter: <hi>O Virgin Daughter of</hi> Egypt, <hi>in vain ſhalt thou uſe many Medicines,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97219:15"/>for thou ſhalt not be cur'd. The Nations have heard of thy ſhame, and thy Cry hath filled the Land, for the Mighty hath ſtumbled againſt the Mighty, and they are fallen both together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much, I ſuppoſe, may be ſufficient to ſhew us, how very remarkable and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful our preſent Deliverance is, conſidering the Circumſtances of it. That which adds to the Remarkableneſs of it, is,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly,</hi> The Conſideration of the People for whom it is wrought. That God ſhould ſignal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear in behalf of a Righteous and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Nation, a Thankful and Obedient Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is agreeable to the Notions we have of him, and is what we are ready to expect from his Providence: But that he ſhou'd do ſo much for an ungrateful People as he has done for us, that he ſhould ſhew himſelf ſo kind to thoſe that have wofully abus'd his Mercies, and that continue ſtill unreform'd in a high degree, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the plain Warnings that he has given 'em, and the loud Calls of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to Repentance and Amendment: This is what may juſtly raiſe our Wonder. But for our Reſolution in the Caſe, that we may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern ſomething of <hi>the Signs of the times,</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97219:16"/>of the true Reaſon, as near as we can judge, of God's Proceeding with us on this manner, and not flatter our ſelves, and impute all to our own good Deſerts, we may do well to Enquire into that which I propos'd as the third Conſideration whereby the Remarkableneſs of our preſent Deliverance, and of this whole Scene of God's Providence, which began with our late Revolution, may farther appear. And that was</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3ly,</hi> What Ends and Deſigns of Providence we may reaſonably ſuppoſe are brought about or anſwered by theſe Events. And here it may be ſit for us to obſerve, that what God has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd and ſoretold as certainly to come to paſs, that he is wont accordingly to bring about, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Sins and Provocations of thoſe for whoſe Benefit it is, and tho' there be but few of them that do in any degree walk wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of ſuch Mercies; For he can find ways enow to puniſh thoſe that do not, without al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering any of his Purpoſes or Decrees. Thus we find that tho' the Poſterity of <hi>Jacob</hi> were extreamly degenerated in <hi>Egypt,</hi> yet God brought 'em out thence,<note place="margin">Exod. 12.41.</note> punctually to a day, at the End of the 430 years, according to his Promiſe. Thus alſo afterwards, tho' they provok'd him highly, inſomuch that he caſt off Ten of their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97219:16"/>Tribes, and the other two were little better, yet he ſtill preſerv'd them as a diſtinct People, tho' made Captives firſt, and afterwards Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries to other Nations, becauſe the ſo doing was neceſſary in order to what he had oft fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told and promis'd, concerning the coming of the Meſſiah. Thus again, 'tis very obſervable, That tho' we can diſcern nothing that was viſible in the Face of things, from whence to gather any like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood of ſuch or ſuch Events coming to paſs, yet God having foretold 'em, we find that ſtill in due time, all things were made to work that way, and ſo as to bring about what he had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd. For inſtance; It having been reveal'd to <hi>Daniel</hi> that there ſhould be four great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies ſet up in the World, (<hi>viz.</hi> Three more beſide that of <hi>Babylon,</hi> which was then in being) the Providence of God did in a very wonderful manner, cauſe it in due time to be effected and brought about. For the overthrow of the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonian</hi> Empire by <hi>Cyrus,</hi> which <hi>Daniel</hi> liv'd to ſee, and of the <hi>Perſian</hi> by <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, carried in 'em very ſignal Characters of a Divine Providence. And ſo did alſo the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up of the fourth and laſt, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empire, from very inconſiderable and low beginnings. It was a long Series and Courſe of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97219:17"/>Succeſſes for many hundred years, which the <hi>Romans</hi> themſelves attributed to Providence, by which their City came at laſt to be the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs of the World: Nor can we diſcern any thing but the meer Will and Decree of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that hindred <hi>Hannibal,</hi> when he gave it ſo terrible a Shock as he did, from quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning it. But he and his People were of the Race of <hi>Cham,</hi> of which it was foretold that they ſhould be Servants, and not bear Rule. And God had alſo deſign'd that the fourth Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy ſhou'd be ſet up at <hi>Rome,</hi> and not at <hi>Carthage.</hi> And therefore though <hi>Hannibal</hi> ſeem'd to be come within a very little of utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroying that State, yet he cou'd not ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it, which drew from him thoſe memorable words recorded by the Hiſtorian, after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding Battle at <hi>Metaurus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Liv.</hi> l. 27. c. 51.</note> 
               <hi>Agnoſco fortunam Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginis.</hi> I ſee 'tis not the Decree of Heaven that <hi>Carthage</hi> ſhould prevail. Or, I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and ſubmit to the Fate of that City.</p>
            <p>If then we have now but ſufficient Reaſon to perſwade us, that 'tis a thing contrary to the Will and Pleaſure of Almighty God, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Reformed Religion ſhou'd be totally extirpated, or that a fifth Univerſal Monarchy ſhou'd be ſet up, We may then ſufficiently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97219:17"/>what Ends of Providence are ſerv'd by the late ſtrange and unexpected Events, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Deſigns of the aſpiring Monarch of our Days have been hitherto blaſted and brought to nought: And, at the ſame time, we may ſee reaſon ſtill the more to obſerve and admire the Hand of God in all theſe things, and to put our Truſt in him for the future.</p>
            <p>Now as for the Deſign of Extirpating the Proteſtant Religion, that we are as ſure is a wicked Deſign, as we are that our Religion is true and good. Yea, both the Deſign, and the barbarous Methods whereby it has been in part effected, are certainly abominable in the ſight of God and Man: The converting of poor People, quiet and loyal Subjects, by Miſſiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Dragoons, being a practiſe that is reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, not to Chriſtianity only, but even unto Humane Nature. But that it is alſo a Deſign which God will not permit to take effect, we may probably gather from what has been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore briefly touch'd concerning the wonderful Providences whereby God kindled the Light of the Reformation but about the beginning of the laſt Age, which 'tis hard to imagine he ſhou'd ſuffer ſo ſoon to be extinguiſh'd again. Yea moreover, ſince we are aſſur'd that God
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97219:18"/>will always have a Church, and the Popiſh one is now ſo extreamly corrupted (ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, worſe in many reſpects than it was before) that it can hardly be call'd a true one, that gives us good ground to believe that God will never ſuffer the Reformation to be utterly deſtroy'd. And yet 'tis hard to ſee but that that wou'd be the plain Conſequence of the <hi>French</hi> Succeſſes, of their over-running theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and ſetting up an Univerſal Monarchy.</p>
            <p>But as for the Deſign of a Fifth Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, it is a thing generally agreed, I think, by all the Interpreters of <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Viſions, as being ſufficiently plain in the Text, that there are to be, and ſhall be but Four; And that whenever they are at an End, the next thing we are to expect, is either the End of the World, or ſuch a Renovation of it as is utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inconſiſtent with the <hi>French</hi> Deſigns. And if ſo, what can we expect, but that God ſhou'd as effectually blaſt all Attempts to ſet it up, as he did thoſe in the laſt Age, of <hi>Philip</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>Spain:</hi> Tho' perhaps in a more extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary and terrible manner, in regard to the Blaſphemies that have been utter'd, and the Outrages that have been offer'd to the Saints and Servants of the moſt High!</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:97219:18"/>
            <p> And thus much, I ſuppoſe may be ſufficient to ſhew us how very remarkable both our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Deliverance is, and alſo all that Scene of Providence of which it is a part: And likewiſe to excite our devout Admiration of the Power, Wiſdom, Goodneſs, and Faithfulneſs of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God as manifeſted therein.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I come now in the laſt place briefly to conſider how very beneficial and happy a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance this is to us, in order to the encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of our Thankfulneſs, and putting us upon a ſuitable Carriage towards God. And tho' we cannot ſay that this Deliverance is ſent us as a Reward of our Good Deſerts, but rather have great reaſon to bewail the contrary Carriage of the generality amongſt us; Yet ſo many as have but ſincerely endeavour'd to do their Duty, and in an humble Sence of the total Dependence of all upon the Divine Providence, have been ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Suitors and Solicitors at the Throne of Grace for Mercy upon theſe ſinful Nations, They may look on this Deliverance as an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to their Prayers, and an Encouragement to 'em to pray ſtill, and to put their Truſt in God. And as for others, it is a great and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Benefit to them, if they have but the hearts to make uſe of it. For 'tis a granting
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97219:19"/>'em farther Reſpite; 'Tis the affording 'em ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Call to Return and Repent, which if they will not hearken to, it is their own Fault; but the kindneſs of Almighty God is never the leſs. Neither let any think, that ſince the Reaſon of this Providence ſeems rather to be God's high Diſpleaſures at the Deſigns of our Enemies, than any reſpect that he has to ſuch a ſinful People as we are, that therefore it ſignifies no great matter whether they reform or not. For doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs tho' he may ſtill go on to defeat thoſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes which are contrary to his Will, yet he can eaſily find Means ſufficient to puniſh all thoſe that are thus harden'd in their Sins, and give them but little cauſe to rejoyce even tho' their Enemies are not ſuffered to attain their Ends. We may ſee already how variouſly God has mix'd good and bad Succeſs in the courſe of this preſent War; the bad ſtill being owing to our ſelves, and an effect of our own Sins, but the good proceeding from an over-ruling Hand of Providence that will not ſuffer our Enemies to have their Will. But now if we wou'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and become a People fit for Mercy, we might hope that God wou'd not only bring down our Enemies, but cauſe us to riſe by their Fall, and grant us that Peace and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97219:19"/>which by our Sins we have ſo juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to forfeit.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, if we conſider but what the Effect muſt have been of our Enemies ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their expected Succeſs in this Enterprize which God has been pleas'd ſo happily to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and defeat, we ſhall find cauſe enough for Joy and Thankſgiving, if there be any Bleſſing we enjoy, which we think deſerves it, ſince there is ſcarce any which their Succeſs wou'd not have depriv'd us of. I know not how ſtrangely ſome People might flatter themſelves, and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that the Reſtoration of the late King, even by a <hi>French</hi> Power, wou'd have been conſiſtent with the Enjoyment of the free Profeſſion of their Religion and their Liberties, that the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Forces ſhou'd quietly have retir'd ſo ſoon as they had ſet him upon the Throne, and that he, laying aſide all former thoughts, wou'd have contented himſelf in taking a little pleaſure to ſee how they wou'd Perſecute and Torment their fellow Proteſtants, and have gone no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. To me this ſeems ſo great a piece of Folly and Extravagance, as needs only to be nam'd in order to it's being expos'd. And therefore I conclude, that if our preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition be better than that of conquer'd Slaves;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97219:20"/>if it be a Happineſs not to fall into the Hands of incens'd and bitter Enemies; if the Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Peace at home, with the hopes of good Succeſs in our Wars abroad; if our Laws and Liberties; yea, if the Light of the Goſpel, and the free Profeſſion of our Religon, be things of any value to us, then ought we to be exceeding thankful to that God who has ſo ſignally appear'd for us, and delivered us in the moſt ſeaſonable and needful time. And that this our Sacrifice of Praiſe and Thankſgiving may be accepted, we ſhou'd add thereto our hearty and ſincere Endeavours to walk worthy of God's Mercies, and ſo to behave our ſelves in all holy Obedience to his Laws, that it may indeed appear, that this great Grace and Favour of his in delivering us ſo oft and ſo ſignally as he has done, has not been beſtow'd in vain up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, nor may ever turn to our greater Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. Which God of his infinite Mercy grant.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97219:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
